A Guide to the Papers of the Albemarle Soapstone Company, 1885-1907 and 1919-1936
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Albemarle Soapstone Company, 1885-1907 and 1919-1936
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11396
ca. 3,450 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear feet)
This collection consists of the business papers of the Albemarle Soapstone Company, Alberene, Virginia, described as manufacturers of Alberene Stone Laundry Tubs & Sinks, and including some of its associate businesses, the Nelson and Albemarle Railway Company and the Virginia Soapstone Company, Schuyler, Virginia, 1885-1907 and 1919-1936. William L. Harrison was the purchasing agent for all three companies. Other products advertised by this company include: sinks, acid tanks, foot warmers, griddles, fireplaces, and register borders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from the Book Broker, Charlottesville, Virginia, on April 10, 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
The massive deposit of soapstone known as the "Albemarle-Nelson Belt," lying between Lynchburg and Charlottesville, with an exposed section near Schuyler, has a greater percentage of workable stone than any other known deposit in the world. By 1900, Nelson County had six working soapstone quarries. In 1893, the Virginia Soapstone Company was incorporated with Max Wiehle as president, and had opened their quarry and mill to work the deposit at Schuyler, Nelson County.
The Albemarle Soapstone Company, in Alberene, Albemarle County, originated from the partnership of James Serene, Brooklyn, New York, and Daniel J. Carroll, a box manufacturer. Having located a large soapstone deposit near Johnson's Mill Gap, Albemarle County, they began development of their "Alberene" stone in 1883. The name of Alberene derived from a combination of Albemarle and Serene, and was coined by Daniel J. Carroll. The village of Johnson's Mill Gap was renamed Alberene. The village grew into a company town complete with a company store selling all sorts of goods.
In 1904, Virginia Soapstone and Albemarle Soapstone became fully merged under the name Virginia Soapstone Company, and by 1916 they became part of the Virginia Alberene Company. After the onset of the Depression, the assets of Virginia Alberene were taken over by the Alberene Stone Corporation of Virginia, which remained in business until the Schuyler plant closed in 1973. It reopened in 1976 with Vance Wilkins as the new owner and Ken Carroll as the general manager. In 1986, the plant was modernized by new owners, the Finnish Soapstone Company, and was renamed The New Alberene Stone Company.
Scope and Content Information
Papers include correspondence, orders and invoices, bound volumes, receipts and accounts, bank checks, company store scrip and scrip receipts, drawings and diagrams of products, and some of the records of the postmaster at the Alberene Post Office, Alberene, Virginia. A large amount of this material is dated 1906-1907, and is concerned with the purchases made by the Albemarle Soapstone Company through William L. Harrison. Earlier material is more likely to consist of orders from other businesses for soapstone products. Also present are eleven time books of the company, which list the names of the employees for the period 1891-1895.
The correspondence files are chiefly concerned with communications about orders and sales between James H. Serene at the home office, 4 and 6 Peck Slip, New York City, George M. Lee at the office and salesroom in Chicago, and the soapstone quarries in Alberene, Virginia. Other letters contain inquiries about the soapstone and orders for specified products. Correspondence of a later date, ca. 1907, include letters from Richard Flynn, from the New York City office, and William L. Harrison, Alberene, Virginia.
Contents List
- Papers re the Albemarle Soapstone Company 1890-1936, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Albemarle Soapstone Company Scrip and Scrip Receipts 1900, n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of the Albemarle Soapstone Company [1888?]-1894 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of the Albemarle Soapstone Company 1905-1907 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Papers 1889-1895, 1919-1936 (Box 1)
    - Registered Letter Receipts, Alberene Post Office 1890-1891, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Orders and Invoices Arranged by Business Name 1889-1908, n.d. (Box 2-5)
    - Adams & Woodson, Lynchburg, Virginia 1889, 1891 (Box 2)
    - Adams Express Company ca. 1890-1907 (Box 2)
    - American Glue Company, Boston, Massachusetts 1907-1908 (Box 2)
    - Bailey-Spencer Hardware Company, Lynchburg, Virginia 1907, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Ballard & Ballard Company, Louisville, Kentucky 1907 (Box 2)
    - Baughman Stationery Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - C.L. Randall & Company, Oxford, Michigan 1907 (Box 2)
    - Carbolane Slate Company, Esmont, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - Carborundum Company, Niagara Falls, New York 1907 (Box 2)
    - Charles King & Son Company, Charlottesville, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - Charlottesville Hardware Company, Charlottesville, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - Charlottesville Lumber Company, Charlottesville, Virginia 1907, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Chesapeake and Ohio Coal & Coke Company, Richmond, Virginia 1892-1907 (Box 2)
    - Clarence Cosby, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - Cliff Weil Cigar Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - The Crane Company, Baltimore, Maryland 1907 (Box 2)
    - Dewey Brothers Company, Blanchester, Ohio 1907 (Box 2)
    - Diuguid & Company, Lynchburg, Virginia 1907 (Box 2)
    - E.B. Taylor Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Eagle Paper Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - Etchison Hat Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - Fairfield Shoe Company, Lancaster, Ohio 1907 (Box 3)
    - Fleenor Furniture Company, Lynchburg, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - Fleming & Christian Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - General Electric Company 1892, 1907 (Box 3)
    - Graton & Knight Manufacturing Company, New York City 1907, n.d. (Box 3)
    - H.C. Marchant Manufacturing Company, Charlottesville, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - H.T. Holladay Merchant Miller, Rapidan, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - J.H. Linney, Charlottesville, Virginia 1907 (Box 3)
    - John H. North Company, Boston, Massachusetts 1907 (Box 3)
    - John J. Greer & Company, Baltimore, Maryland 1907 (Box 3)
    - Joseph Dixon Crucible Company, Jersey City, New Jersey 1907 (Box 3)
    - Keystone Blue Paper Company, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 1907 (Box 3)
    - Louis Grebb Oyster & Fruit Packer, Baltimore, Maryland 1907 (Box 3)
    - Manning, Maxwell & Moore, Inc., New York City 1907, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Companies A-J 1889-1907 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Companies L-W 1890-1907 (Box 4)
    - N & W Manufacturing Company, Lynchburg, Virginia 1907 (Box 4)
    - Nelson Morris & Company, Lynchburg, Virginia 1907 (Box 4)
    - Powers Taylor Drug Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 4)
    - R.C. Vandegrift & Son, Charlottesville, Virginia 1890-1893 (Box 4)
    - Richmond & Danville Railroad Company, North Garden Station—Freight Receipts 1889-1894 (Box 4)
    - Richmond & Danville Railroad Company, North Garden Station—Statements 1889-1894, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Robinson, Tate & Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 4)
    - S.T. Beveridge & Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 5)
    - Sanders Brothers Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 5)
    - Scottsville Merchandise Company, Scottsville, Virginia 1907 (Box 5)
    - Smith Brothers, North Garden, Virginia 1906-1907, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Southern Railway Company 1894-1907 (Box 5)
    - Standard Fashion Company, New York City 1907 (Box 5)
    - Stokes-Grymes Grocery Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 5)
    - Strother Drug Company, Lynchburg, Virginia 1907 (Box 5)
    - Studebaker Brothers Company, New York City 1907 (Box 5)
    - T.W. Wood & Sons, Richmond, Virginia 1907 (Box 5)
    - Tower-Binford Electric & Manufacturing Company, Richmond, Virginia 1907, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Traymore Tailoring Company, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 1907 (Box 5)
    - Union Central 1906 (Box 5)
    - W.T. Thompson, New York City 1907 (Box 5)
    - Walworth Manufacturing Company, Boston, Massachusetts 1907 (Box 5)
    - Westinghouse Machine Company, East Pittsburg, Pennsylvania 1907 (Box 5)
    - Wilson Memindex Company, Rochester, New York 1907 (Box 5)
- Bound Volumes and Oversize 1885-1936, n.d. (Box 6-7, oversize folder)
  - Cash Account Book 1893 Nov-1896 Jun (Box 6)
  - Check Register issued by Peoples National Bank, Charlottesville, Virginia 1906-1907 (Box 6)
  - Memoranda Books n.d., 2 vols (Box 6)
  - Mill and Quarry Books 1891-1894, 3 vols (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous bound volumes ca. 1891-1894 (Box 6)
    "Farm Merchandise Cartage Book," "Mr. Dawber's Company House Book," and "Tenement House Repairs"
  - Postmaster's Account & Cash Book 1930-1936, 2 vols (Box 6)
  - Postmaster's Account & Record Book, kept by F.L. Felter, Alberene, Virginia 1898-1901 (Box 6)
  - Record of Registered Letters 1898-1899 (Box 6)
  - Soapstone Production/Stock Books 1892, n.d., 3 vols (Box 6)
  - Receipt & Account File (Bound), boxed out of alphabetical order due to size of volume 1885-1887 (Box 7)
  - Stock Books, possibly for the Company Store ca. 1891-1894, n.d., 6 vols (Box 7)
  - Time Books of the Albemarle Soapstone Company 1891-1895, 11 vols (Box 7)
  - Unidentified Records 1900 Dec-1901 Feb, 2 vols (Box 7)
  - Record of Registered Letters Received & Delivered ca. 1898-1899?, damaged and fragile; caution when using